<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short relation of the rise and progress of the Turkish warrs in Hungaria, Austria, Moravia, Silesia and Bohemia from the yeare 1359 to the end of the yeare 1663 : with a supplement, or, description of the said countrey, and a mapp vvherein the cities, tovvnes and rivers of the same are explained.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B29793</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12745296</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205196</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240962383</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3622A</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12745296</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B29793)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205196)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1536:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short relation of the rise and progress of the Turkish warrs in Hungaria, Austria, Moravia, Silesia and Bohemia from the yeare 1359 to the end of the yeare 1663 : with a supplement, or, description of the said countrey, and a mapp vvherein the cities, tovvnes and rivers of the same are explained.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 38 p. : ill., map.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>To be sold in St. Pauls Churchyard ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Leicensed the 24 of April 1664, by Roger L'Estrange" -- Verso t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Turkey --  History, Military.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Hungary --  History --  1000-1683.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205196:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205196:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>Short Relation</hi> Of the Rise and Progress <hi>Of the</hi> TURKISH WARRS In <hi>Hungaria, Austria, Moravia, Silesia</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> From the yeare 1359 to the end of the yeare 1663.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a SƲPPLEMENT Or</hi> Description of the said Countrey, and a Mapp wherein the Cities, Townes and Rivers of the same are Explained.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be sold in <hi>St Pauls</hi> Churchyard, at the signe of the Queens Arms, near the litle North-Door of <hi>St Pauls</hi> Church, 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:205196:2"/>
            <p>Leicensed</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>the 24 of April 1664,</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>by Roger L'Estrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:205196:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205196:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>map of Poland and Hungary</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:205196:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205196:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A short Relation of the Rise &amp; Progress</hi> Of the TURKISH WARRS, In Hungaria, Austria, Moravia, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesia and Bohemia.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>From the yeare 1359, to the end of the yeare 1663.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Kingdome of Hungary having been for many ages as a Wall to Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome against the Turkes, was in the yeare 1395 first invaded by the Sarasens, King Sigismund being▪ defeated in that yeare, (though hee had gotten a powerfull Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my together) and yet he was farr worse beaten in the yeare 1409 by the Turkes. In the yeare 1439 Amurath the Turkish Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour came before Senderyn, situated on the Donaw being a Citie belonging to Georg Despota; Lord of that Country, who durst not attend the Turkes comming, but fled out of the Citie, leaving his two Sonnes therein, to defend the same: Hee wrote to the Emperour for assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance but it was then too late, for the Sarasens soone tooke the said place in by a storme, and caused the said two Sonnes Eyes to be put out, and afterwards to be guelded, putting to the Sword besides all the inhabitants. Anno 1441 Iohn Huniadar Corvinus (whose Father was a native Wallachian, but his Mother a Grecian Woman) being the Emperours Generall in Transilvania; cut off in a Village 20000 Turkes, amongst whome was killed the Turkish Bashaw and his Sonne, whose heads Corvinus caused to be stuck upon a Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205196:5"/> (which was soe full of Turkes heads that ten Horses could hardly draw it) which said Treasure hee in that manner presented to the German Emperour; In the yeare 1442 &amp; 43. did Corvinus again courageously beate the Turkes out of the feild. Anno 1444 Ulad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>slaus the King of Hungary broke the peace with the Turkes (being thereunto incited by Pope. Eugenius who wrote unto him that hee was not obliged to keep his Oath with Infidels) and took the feild (all though against the advice of <hi>Corvinus</hi> who proposed to him what a shame it was to breake his Oath, which, even the very Turkes did keepe, and how much more Christians ought to doe so, But the King being backed by the Legat <hi>Julianus,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spised the Councell of <hi>Corvinus,</hi> and marched forwards: Now the Turkes hearing that the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> was soe perfideous, came hastely over the <hi>Hellespont</hi> with 100000 Men, whom the Masters and Pilots of Genoa (having for each Turke a piece of Gold) waif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted over before <hi>Vladislaus</hi> was aware of it: upon St Martins Eve the Christians and Turkes joined Battle, and the Turks at first were put to flight, and <hi>Amurath</hi> the Turkish Emperour also flying, who seeing a Crucifix in one of their Ensignes, cryed out aloude <hi>O thou crucified Christ if thou art the Son of God, powre downe thy wrath upon this King and his people, for hee hath most perfideously broken the Oath, which hee hath sworne by thy Name and holy Gospel.</hi> Behold now there the Turkes flying, and their Camells full of Treasure dispersed, the Bishop of Erland and Waradin fall on to plunder, but the King desirous to follow the Victory, not<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>withstanding <hi>Corvinus</hi> shewed him the danger thereof (and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled him to the contrary) with certain Horse followeth the persuite, which a Janisary perceving, who knew him, shot his Horse under him, and soe killed the said perfideous King, cutting of his head, and stuck it upon a long Speare; Thus sped that peace-brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Monarch of <hi>Hungary,</hi> whose guard endeavoured to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scued him, but in vaine: All the Christians in number about 30000 were that very day by the Turkish Emperour hemmed in and cut off and the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Kings head, (who was but 20 years old) was carried into Turkey. Anno 1445 <hi>Corvinus</hi> was made Vice-Roy of <hi>Hungary,</hi> who having confederated himselfe with the Prince
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205196:5"/> Scanderbeg, did in the yeare 1448 cut of 34000 Turkes in three dayes space, but the last day the Dice turned and <hi>Corvinus</hi> with many Christians where beaten, and hee in his flight being attacqued by two Murtherers (who both quarrelled about the faire and great Gold Crosse which hunge about his Necke, <hi>Corvinus</hi> wrung one of their Scymiters out of their hands, wherewith hee killed the one of them and caused the other (having disarmed him) to fly: hee retyring himselfe, was by <hi>Despota</hi> taken prisoner and not dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, until hee had delivered over his Sonn Uladislaus as Hosta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge; But hee did shortly after well reward the <hi>Despota</hi> by visiting him, with an Army, so that the <hi>Despota</hi> was glad (with many gifts and presents) to restore him his Sonne againe. Anno 1452 <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus</hi> silently retired into <hi>Hungary,</hi> where King <hi>Ʋladislaus</hi> (who now was but 12 yeares old) reigned, to whom hee resigned up his Vice-Royship of <hi>Transilvania,</hi> but the King would perforce that hee should keep it, and gave him also the Earldome or County of <hi>Bistrice:</hi> which great honor the Earle of <hi>Celien</hi> envying, hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused <hi>Corvinus</hi> as if hee aspired to the Crowne of <hi>Hungary,</hi> and sought the life of his Majesty; but <hi>Corvinus</hi> being advertised there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, did so cunningly worke himselfe through all these obstacles, that the Accuser was imprisoned, and hee triumphantly continued in his honour. Anno 1456 the Turkish Emperour Mahomet, who had been made Roman Emperour, by his Father, upon condition, that hee should be, and ever remaine an unreconcileable enemy of the name of JESUS: Three yeares after hee tooke <hi>Constantinople</hi> from the Christians, massacring almost all hee found, and caused all the Borders of Christendome by his Vagabonds and Straglers to be harrased, and miserably destroyed. <hi>Ʋladislaus</hi> the <hi>Hungarian</hi> King, fearing that those invasions might apparently take hold of, and breake into <hi>Vienna,</hi> tooke care thereof; but none save <hi>Corvinus</hi> alone, knew any remedy to oppose the Turkish powers, hee advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and strengthened himselfe with Cardinal <hi>Joannes,</hi> Legate of Pope <hi>Calixto,</hi> and certaine German forces, unto whom joyned <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistranus</hi> an Italian by birth (who was both cunning and curagious, but a meere Hypocrite and dissembler) with 600 Polanders, who adored him as an Idoll, with these and other Troopes did they in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205196:6"/> the yeare 1456, attempt to releive <hi>Stoel-VVeissenburgh,</hi> which was beseiged by <hi>Mahomet: Corvinus</hi> got into it, and encouraged the Garrison, and sallyed out the 6<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of August, in which conflict <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi> himselfe was wounded in his Eye, and carried dead into his Tent, which they set on fire and so most shamefully left the Seige, hereupon <hi>Corvinus</hi> sallyes out agayn, but returning backe, and being too much wearied, departed this life the 10 of September, having been a faithfull Servant of Christendome; Count <hi>Ʋlrich</hi> of <hi>Celien</hi> hearing of this, stirreth the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> up, against the two surviving Sonnes of <hi>Corvinus.</hi> Anno 1457 the King and Count <hi>Celien</hi> meeting together at <hi>Greek-VVeissenburgh</hi> to devide the Spoyle gotten from the Turkes <hi>Ʋladislaus, Corvinus</hi> eldest Sonne fell at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance, first in words with the said Count of <hi>Celien,</hi> and afterwards to blowes, in so much that <hi>Vladislaus</hi> runn Count <hi>Celien</hi> thorough▪ <hi>Vladislaus</hi> Mother did by reason hereof on her knees begg pardon of the King and obtained it, his Majesty soon after commanding, that they should all put of their mourning weeds, and put on Purple Robes embroidered with Gold, which the King gave them as a reward of their Fathers demerits; But they afterwards travai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from <hi>Offen</hi> towards <hi>Hungary,</hi> thinking that all was pacified, were by the King (who was incensed by fresh Accusers) taken Prisoners, and caused <hi>Vladislaus</hi> most cruelly to bee beheaded in the feilds, without any processe of Law; and <hi>Mathias</hi> the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest brother to be conveyed a Prisoner in strong Chaines to <hi>Vienna.</hi> One thing was observable, that the Headsman when hee should execute <hi>Ʋladislaus,</hi> struck him three blowes without fetching Blood, and though hee protested his innocency, hee was never the less dispatched. But God to whom Vengeance alwayes belongeth, punished that King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> for in the yeare 1458, as he was travelling to <hi>Prague</hi> to marry with that incredible precious Princess <hi>Magdalen,</hi> Daughter of the King of France, hee (being then but 18 yeares old) was in the space of thirty houres in health and dead, beeing upon 24 of November destroyed by Poyson; But <hi>Mathias</hi> was miraculously delivered by his Unckle, who sent to the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> 50000 Hungary gilders, by which hee was not onely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, but the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> gave him his daughter to Wife,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205196:6"/> by which meanes <hi>Mathias</hi> himselfe came to be the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> and was succesfull in his Warrs against the Turkes, not withstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that the Polander much envyed him, who himselfe would have had the Hungarian Crowne on his head; but was in the yeare 1463 at Bania shott with an Arrow in the backe. Anno 1481 the Turkish Emperour Mahomet deceased of a great fit of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, which continued three dayes. Anno 1490 dyed King <hi>Mathias,</hi> having greived himselfe too much about some harsh words which he had used against one of his Servants. Anno 1520 the Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians more and more declining mocked and shamefully intreated the Turkish Embassadors, whereupon a Warr ensues, in which the Turkes won <hi>VVeissenburgh,</hi> beating King <hi>Lodowick:</hi> a Monck by his too much bragging being the loss of this, (his name was <hi>Tomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rewes,</hi>) because hee performed not his promise in time, and King <hi>Lodowick</hi> stumbling in a hole in the Water called <hi>Drabmarr</hi> (which was but a spann and a halfe deepe) though comming out, was thrown backward and his Horse fell upon him, under which hee at last was smothered; That villainous Monck two Bishops, and fowre other heads, were carryed through the Turkish Leaguer, and amongst o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the head of <hi>Ladislaus Soleani</hi> Archbishop of <hi>Gran,</hi> who would very faine have left a great Treasure behinde him, without assisting the King therewith, the Turkish Emperour saying, <hi>That Francis Bary Bishop of VVaradyn had done better, by warning the King against this Battle;</hi> and seeing a piece of Hungary money upon which both the King and Queene of <hi>Hungary</hi> (who where both of them young) coyned or instamped, is said to have been grieved, that his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell had not advised him aginst that feild Battle, he not beeing come into <hi>Hungary</hi> to prejudice the King <hi>Lodowick,</hi> but to a venge the spitefull usage shewed to his Embassadours, and that hee (if <hi>Lodowick</hi> had been alive) would willingly have assigned the whole Kingdome to him, upon a small Tribute, because hee had been deceived and sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by his owne people; but the Turkes when they speak faire are not to be trusted for they did afterwards winn <hi>Pest</hi> and <hi>Offen;</hi> which King <hi>Ferdinand</hi> 1527 rewonn, but lost the same againe, and also <hi>Comorra.</hi> Anno 1529 came Solyman before <hi>Vienna,</hi> of which the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbes were burned, it had yet 20000 foote Souldiers, and 2000
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205196:7"/> Horse therein: <hi>Solyman</hi> the Turkish Emperour demanded the City to be surrendred, but they answered him, that they by Gods grace would defend the said City to the last Man, whereupon <hi>Soly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> came with 400 Ships downe the Donaw, and with slight Cannon, caused all the Bridges to be throwne downe: the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians had but ill success then, yet after that 636 Citizens had been killed, the Turkes upon the 14 of <hi>October</hi> 1529 left the Seige after the Christians had there lost 1500 Men; then the Turkish Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour returned to <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and made <hi>John Vayvod</hi> at <hi>Offen</hi> King of <hi>Hungaria:</hi> The Turks had before that time taken the City <hi>Offen</hi> without blow or push, the <hi>Germans</hi> not making one shot, which much troubled <hi>Thomas Nodasti</hi> their Governour, <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> himselfe praising <hi>Nodasties</hi> faithfulness, and gave him, (though hee was his Prisoner) his life, But the <hi>Germans</hi> when they were marched out (although he promised them their lives) did hee cause to be killed in the feilds, for their perfideousnes, thereby punishing the falsitie of Soldiers, whilst hee as Turkish Emperour committed falsnes, by breaking his promise, made to the German Soldiers: <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyman</hi> did then also winn <hi>Comorra</hi> and the well fortified Citie <hi>Alten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</hi> Anno 1532 the Turkes beleaguered <hi>Gran,</hi> and did much dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stresse it, but where as the Woemen and Children who were fled into the Castle made a great noyse and crye, the Turke, thinking, that there were still very many Soldiers in the Citie, did therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part▪ and left the Seige. Anno 1537 were the <hi>Imperialists</hi> beaten by <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>homet,</hi> because <hi>John Catzianer</hi> Generall o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Crabates</hi> plaid the part of a faithless man, leaving <hi>Lodowick Lodron</hi> in the danger, who carried himselfe so manfully, that hee cut the hamstrings of his owne Horse, thereby to give an example to his Soldiers, that hee would not ride nor runne away, but stand by them to the death; hee was (manfully fighting) at length taken prisoner, cut in pieces, and his head sent to <hi>Constantinople: Catziaus</hi> thought to excuse himselfe, but was apprehended, though cutting the sheet's of his Bed into pieces, he escaped out of his Chamber, and ran to the Turkes, (who upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, of delivering over some Cities in <hi>Austria</hi>) confirmed him to be Generall in <hi>Croatia;</hi> hee thereby thought to induce <hi>Nicholas</hi> Earle of <hi>Seryn</hi> to doe the like, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this brave Champion would not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205196:7"/> breake his Oath, which hee had sworne to the Emperour, but did after dinner cause this Traytor to be murthered, and sent his head to the Emperour, by reason whereof this noble family of the <hi>Seryns</hi> which indeed are brave Souldiers, were by the Emperour dignified with the Castle of <hi>Catzianer</hi> and all his goods.</p>
            <p>Anno 1540. <hi>Iohn</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> deceasing, left a Widdow and 2 Son of eleaven dayes old behind him, the Christians called him <hi>Steven</hi> but the Turkes <hi>Iohn Issabella,</hi> the Widdow was by a Monck whose name was <hi>Iurian,</hi> perswaded, that both of them should take the Crowne of <hi>Hungary</hi> upon their heads; The Monck being cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, though poore, yet of a noble house of <hi>Croatia,</hi> and educated by the deceased King <hi>Iohns</hi> Mother, being ashamed to serve other men, retired himselfe into a Monastery at <hi>St Paul</hi> learning as much Latin as that hee could say the Masse: 'tis true that King <hi>Iohn</hi> made much of him; and <hi>Iuriaen</hi> the Monck carried himselfe well, in so much that the King made him his Steward over <hi>Transilvania,</hi> and gave him the Bishoprick of <hi>VVaradyn;</hi> but this Monck and the Queen fearing that the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> in persuite of the peace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded betweene <hi>Austria</hi> and <hi>Hungaria</hi> would endeavour to make himselfe Master of <hi>Hungary,</hi> sent in the name of the young Son (whom they pretended to desire that he should remaine King of <hi>Hungary</hi>) to the Turkish Emperour, a two yeares contribution, namely a tun of Gold, and one hundred silver gilt dishes, forty Cotes embroidered with Gold and Sylver, after the Turkish fashion, and thirty pound weight of beaten Gold; whereby they obtained great assistance against the German Emperour in somuch, that anno 1541 the Turkes won <hi>Pest</hi> out of which the inhabitants as if they had been persued rann away in so much that the River <hi>Donaw</hi> turned read with their blood, loosing thereby 2500 Men, and 186 pieces of Cannon. <hi>Solyman</hi> the Turkish Emperour being incensed by some of his Soldiers (in despite of the Emperour of <hi>Austria</hi>) caused the Christian Prisoners to be massacred; but sent to the Queen of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> and his freind the Moncke great presents, desiring to see her cheife Lords and Son in his Leaguer, the Monck doth not councel the Queen to the contrary thereof but promiseth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine surety, that her son should be by <hi>Solyman</hi> returned to his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205196:8"/> Mother; though when they were come thither, and whilst <hi>Solyman</hi> kindly yet deceiptfully entertained them, and the Lords who accompanied them; he overmastered the Citie <hi>Offen;</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards hee sent the young King backe againe, but detained the Lords who brought him thither, and made the Monck Treasurer: the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> did then begg to obtaine <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venbergen</hi> of him, but yet in vaine, The Moncke <hi>Iuriaen</hi> having got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in all liklyhood his will of the Queen, maintained her very meanly, in so much, that shee complained to the Emperour of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key (for shee could not sustaine her selfe with that which <hi>Iuriaen</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed her, but <hi>Solyman</hi> caused care to be taken of her which so much grieved the Moncke; that he said to the Earle of <hi>Solms,</hi> that hee knew a way to bereave the Queen (although shee was the Daughter of <hi>Sigismund</hi> King of <hi>Poland</hi>) of all her Kingdoms. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon began a Warr in <hi>Transilvania,</hi> wherein the Inhabitants incline to the Traytor and desert the Queen; But yet the <hi>Secklers</hi> a trustie people, remaining faithfull to the Queene, forced the Moncke to an agreement; afterwards <hi>Iuriaen</hi> became perjured, and hee seeketh as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the German Emperour, who in the yeare 1548 won <hi>Erlan:</hi> In the yeare 1551 the Moncke had so much seduced the Emperour, that the King of <hi>Stoel - VVeissenburgh</hi> constrained the Queen to agree with <hi>Iuriaen</hi> and to surrender <hi>Transilvania,</hi> to him, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> was to give her for a present the summe of 150000 Hungary Crownes yearely, and yearely to her Son 25000 Crownes, and that the Queene should incorporate the City <hi>Casha,</hi> but afterwards the truth appeared, for when the King at Table re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the Emperours Generall <hi>Castoldo,</hi> that <hi>Iuriaen</hi> the Moncke was the occasion of all those troubles, hee a moneth after fell of from the Emperour, and in the interim a Turkish <hi>Bashaw</hi> intended to have taken the Queene prisoner; But it sped not, and in the meane tyme was <hi>Transilvania</hi> conveyed over to the Emperour, at which the Turke was incensed, and not being content with the agreement betweene the Emperour and the Queen, thereupon followed a great Warr in <hi>Transilvania,</hi> in which the Monck appeareth in the feild; and at the Emperours earnest intreaty, <hi>Iurian</hi> the grand knave was by Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> the third made Cardinall, who by credit of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205196:8"/> hath acted very prejudicially against Christendome, in so much, as there were several designed to make him away, to which end <hi>Castal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Palavicino</hi> one of the Imperial Colonells, comming to <hi>Bintz</hi> to advise with the Monck, concerning the management of the Imperiall Army, and not being satisfied with the Moncks opinions concerning the same, <hi>Castaldo</hi> departed from the Monck in a great discontent, and comming by <hi>Andreas Loperean</hi> another Commander of the Army, told how necessary it was, that the Monck should be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spatcht out of the way, or al <hi>Hungary</hi> would be lost. Both agree with 24 Spanish soldiers, to surprise some Towres of the City, and order several Troops to be in a readiness, neer to the gates of the Citie of <hi>Bintz,</hi> and that night it was observed that the River was swel'd so high, that it was never knowne before in the memory of the eldest in the Citie, at which the Monck himself was not a little troubled; in the morning as the Moncks Waggons did usualy goe out of the gates of the Citie, for provisions, severall <hi>Heyduks</hi> cloathed in turkish habits to hyde their Armes, came into the Cittie, and <hi>Palavici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> attended with some trustie spanish Soldiers, came very early to the Moncks Lodgings, desiring to speak with the Monck, having in their company (for to avoyd suspition) an other Spaniard who was the Moncks Secretary, who having a letter in his hand, was immediatly admitted into the Moncks Chamber: <hi>Palavicino</hi> stepping after, held the dore so that it might not be shut againe, the Secretary comming to the Monck, who was leaning upon a Table in his night-Gowne, desired leave of him to goe with the Marckgraef <hi>Palavicino</hi> to <hi>Vienna,</hi> and if hee pleased to command him any service thither, giving him the letter he carryed in his hand, and desiring him to read it, which while the Monck was doing, the Secretary being behind him, strooke this Monck with his Dagger upon the shoulder, soe that it came throw his breast and out neere his throat whereupon the Monck creyed out <hi>O Iesu Mary:</hi> and struck the Secretary upon his breast, insomuch that hee fell backward against the corner of the Table, the Marquis hearing the noyse, Suddenly stepped with his naked sword into the Chamber, and with a mighty blow cleft his head asunder, the other Spanyards entering in, killed him outright, after hee had first bitterly wept, <hi>O Iesus Mary our Lady: my deare bretheren where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205196:9"/> doe you this?</hi> Thus punished God one by the other: those who murthered the Monck remained not unpunished, for <hi>Palavicino</hi> was taken Prisoner by the Turkes, and caried away into Slavery: two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of them was beheaded in France, an other was for his falshood quartered, and an other was killed by a wild Boar: And the Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Transilvania</hi> fell afterwards into greater misery then ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: The Turkish Emperour understanding the Moncks death, who had been very serviceable to him in many things (to the prejudice of Christendume) became very sorrowfull, and the more, because the Christians became masters of all the Moncks fortresses and riches, whereupon hee in his turkish wrath, swore by Mahomet to avenge the same upon <hi>Transilvania,</hi> for it vexed him sorely, that 250000 Crownes which the said Monck left behinde him, and also 50000 Crownes lying amongst the Officers at <hi>Bints, VVaradyn, Vivar</hi> and <hi>Deve,</hi> came into the hands of the Christians: although the German Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> did very justly command, that all such summes as hee had in his life time taken from the Queene, should be again payd unto her, out of the Moncks relict goods, and did also out of the same goods richly reward those who murthered the Monck, and did cause the rest of the Gold and Silver to be melted, and Hungary money to be coyned thereof, which peeces or kinde of mony as being of good allowance, did long afterwards cause the Hungary Ducats and smaller pieces to be well esteemed of. On the other side the Pope was angry that the Emperours Folkes had killed the Monck, and did therefore despise the Emperours Embassadours, hee thinking it to be an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible thing, that because he had given the Moncke a Cardinalls hat, he was therefore virtuous in all his dealings, as if that understanding and virtue were entailed to that dignity, and hee caused the Emperour, for that cause to be sharply reprehended, that hee caused a person so well qualified, and renowned in Europe, to bee murthered. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> as an obedient Sonn of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> fearing to enrage the Pope promised to demonstrate the just demerit of the Monck, and that the manifold villanies by him committed were more then certain enough, but it availed nought, because the Pope required that they should have made him Heire of the Monks Estate, for he sent to that end three expresse Legates from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Austria,</hi> that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205196:9"/> they should send him over a true Inventory of all the Moncks relict goods; But the Germans answered the couvetous Legates, that the Military persons were paid therewith, and that there was not so much found, as they had made the Pope beleeve. This did the Legates write over to the Pope, who being thereby the more inraged, said, that the sinns of the Murtherers of the Monck, should never be forgiven: notwithstanding that there were severall originall Letters shewed to the said Legates, which the said Moncke had in his lifetime, (to the shame of the Christians) exchanged with the Turkes, in one of which amongst the rest, stood written as followeth, <hi>That he had agreed with</hi> Solyman <hi>the Turkish Emperour, that he should have caused him (although but a Monck) to be crowned King of</hi> Hungary, <hi>and that alone with this condition, that hee should pay but a small Tribute to Solyman.</hi> In the meane while, the Turke accordingly as hee had threatned presently invaded <hi>Transilvania,</hi> taketh <hi>Temeswar, Sobuch</hi> and <hi>Solnoch;</hi> besieged <hi>Erlan,</hi> in which place, the Woman aswell as the Men demonstrated their courage, for defence of their Countrie, for they made in the Citie a mutuall and solemne Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to that end one with another: 1. That upon paine of death no peace should be made with the Turkes, 2. That no man should yield themselves to the Turkes, 3. Neither give any other answer to them then by shooting against them, 4. That if by famine they were compelled to each others Flesh; that it should be noe sham to any one. 5. That Woman as well as Men should worke at the fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the releife of sicke and wounded persons. 6. That for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of all treason it was ordered that but 3 or 4 persons should assemble together, or talke privatly, being alwayes mindefull how they ought to fight for their Countrey. 7. That all provisions should be to each one equally divided. 8. That all Poultrey and choisest fare, should be onely preserved for the sicke and wounded persons: Those of <hi>Erlan</hi> being thus resolved, did manfully resist thirteen most bloody Stormes; and although <hi>Mahomet Bashaw</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them all favours and Priviledges, yet they contemned the same, and gave no other answer unto his fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttering promises, but shewed him a dead Beare, covereth with a mourning Cloath, which they lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up, upon two speares above the Walles, giving him thereby to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205196:10"/> understand, that they would rather manfully within the Walls die for the defence of the Citie, then leaving the same become slaves to the Turkes, or die as faithless Christians. And these Rules were thus registred in their records. In this Seige it happened, that a Woman standing upon the Walls, her Husband was shott dead downe by her side, at which shee being undaunted, would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Walls to bury her Husband, before shee had taken her revenge upon the Turkes for it, to which end shee did presently disrobe her Husband of his Armes, and put them upon her selfe, and was not satisfied before shee had killed three Turkes with her owne hands, and then shee caused her Husband to be bury<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in the Church. Another Wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in this Seige carrying a greate Stone upon her head, to fling downe upon the <hi>Sarasens</hi> who were storming, her head was shott of: her Daughter standing by her side, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing shee was much bloodied with the shot, made at her mother, tooke up the same stone, and killed two Turkes, and wounded other two therewith; whereby shee wholly forgot her mothers death. Anno 1556 wonn the Turkes <hi>Stoel-VVeissenburgh.</hi> Anno 1558 <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> was Elected Emperour in <hi>Charles</hi> the fifths place, and after him <hi>Maximilian,</hi> who quitted himselfe well against the Turkes, but the most detestable thing was, that the Hungarians themselves, out of malice to each other encouraged the Turkes, in so much that they cruelly plagued <hi>Hungary, Transilvania, VVallachia,</hi> and other parts, practising about nothing else but to spoile <hi>Europe,</hi> and sought by divers wayes and meanes (though in vaine) to obtaine the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the Northerne and Westerne Christians: 'Tis true they procured some who assisted them with Gunnpowder and Cannon, and also some Ingeniers, and fireworkes, by the way of Muscovie, intending thereby to have forced the strong forteresse <hi>Sigeth:</hi> which the Count <hi>Seryn</hi> understanding, and having understood their incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation thereunto severall yeares before, hee stopt up the Gates of the place with earth and tooke an oath to the death of the Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sens, that they would never lysten to the Turkes, in so much, that when as the Turkes sometimes, though they had advanced or got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten some what, hee defended the place very manfully, and though the <hi>Sarasens</hi> in one▪ day saw above 300 Turkes heads stucke upon speares
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205196:10"/> about the Walls at which sight their courage and force to fight was lost, they yet attempted to perswade &amp; bribe the same Count <hi>Seryn</hi> by money (though in vaine) to deliver over the said place: In the meane time <hi>Solyman</hi> the Turkish Emperour dieth: the Turkes (according to their deceiptfull nature) shewed the Soldiers the Corps in a Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin, pretending that those who saw him, and stormed <hi>Sigeth,</hi> should be assisted by the deceased <hi>Solyman,</hi> and become masters of the place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Janisaries in this matter the most earnest, fell on manfully upon the Castle, but they found by the manfull resistance themselves won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully deceived. Then Count <hi>Seryn</hi> was again by the Garrison very much pressed, and demanded, why they so long should with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand soe great force, the Soldiers pretending, that they lived but by their wages and the Oath, the Count seeing their discontent, and that there was noe othet issue, but death to be expected, he put on a darke purple Suite of Cloathes, tooke the Keyes of the Castle, and a 100 Hungary Gilders; the Imperial Ensignes, his Semiter and Target, and laying them by him, he sent for the Souldiers, leaning with his arme upon the said Armes and Keyes, he spake to them in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>These things which I yet have by me, and still in my power, shall never (as long as the Almighty▪ spareth my health) be taken from me for I am ready for the defence thereof to fight till death, &amp;c:</hi> The Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers being hereby encouraged, continue in their fidelity, so long till at last, the Count <hi>Seryn</hi> after severall wounds by him received, died of three shott which he got in his head, by which meanes the fortresse <hi>Sigeth</hi> was won by the Turkes. Anno 1570 a Peace was concluded, between the German Emperour and the Turkish Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: And the Turkish Emperour <hi>Sultan Selym,</hi> having reigned eight yeares deceased, almost about the same time, when <hi>Rudolphus</hi> was made King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi> Anno 1576 dyed the Emperour <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> at the dyet at <hi>Regensburgh,</hi> when as the truce with the Turkes was prolonged from eight to sixteen yeares: Anno 1586, was all along the River <hi>Donaw</hi> a great famine, and foure yeare after happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned eight or 9 Earthquakes. Then came <hi>Hasan Bashaw</hi> of <hi>Bosnia</hi> before <hi>Canisa,</hi> by <hi>Isdrin,</hi> dissembling at first not to take the place, but marched up against the Cloyster of <hi>Zagabria,</hi> which he battered with 24 pieces of Cannon, but because the said Cloyster was soe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205196:11"/> well situated betweene the Rivers, the <hi>Saru</hi> and <hi>Culpa,</hi> he could not obtaine it. The Turke seeing of how much concernement this place might be to him, and not willing to let fall so dainty abit, sent many rich presents to the Commander thereof, and also infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him that the secrets of their Cloyster had been long since made knowne to him, the said Commander growing jealous of such boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stings, examined every one in the Cloyster, to trye if any of them kept any correspondence with the Turkes, and at last found out that the cheife head of the Cloyster was the person who kept intelligence witn the Turkes, who also five yeares before had taken money of the Turkes to betray the same; hee was presently imprisoned, and was in presence of those who were sent from the Turkes throwne alive downe out of a high Window of the said Cloyster, into the River the <hi>San,</hi> and there drowned: There was no other answer given to the Turkes, but that they shewed them all their Cannon and Armes: They returning brought back the newes of all to the Turke who seeing himselfe thus cheated and mocked, became much enraged, and endeavored to winn the place, both by subtilitie and under hand dealing, for he well knew how much the place concerned him. And wrote therefore to the Commander, that he should pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide himselfe of some faithfull persons, and appoint a day and time to treate with him in due forme about the surrender of the Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</p>
            <p>And now the Turkish Emperour having overcome many Castles and Strengths, most by subtilitie: upon the 9 of <hi>July</hi> gave the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Army a great defeate, the Sunne having the day before appeared blood-red in the Firmament, from the morning to the Evening: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the terrour of the Turkes grew soe exceeding great in <hi>Styre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> and <hi>Croatia,</hi> that at this time it happened in the cheife Citie <hi>Labbath, Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Croatia,</hi> that certain mad Companions came there and made the Citie beleeve, that the Turkes were come before the Gates: The Inhabitants being thereby much a frighted threw all their best goods into Cartes and Waggons, and soe fled out of the Citie, which they wholly forsooke, those Mothers who had many Children and could not take them along with them, at their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture kissed them as if they should never againe have seene them,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205196:11"/> many of them aswell Women as Children, were by their hasty flight trodden under footeby Horses, But when they were come just out of the Citie, and assured that it was all false, they returned backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain into their Citie and Houses. The German Emperour <hi>Rudol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,</hi> finding himselfe too weake, to resist the Turkes, requested as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance of the German Princes, and obtaines it, But his Army of 7000 men was upon the 17 of <hi>September</hi> totally routed, in somuch, that but 84 Men of them escaped, who for feare, of being cut in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces like the rest, hid themselves in a certaine Chappel, amongst the dead Mens bones. Then won also the Turkes the fort <hi>St George:</hi> the 12 of <hi>June</hi> were the Turkes by the River <hi>Culpa</hi> shamefully bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the Christians, leaving behind them much Cannon, and great Booty; the provision Ships, many other shipping upon the <hi>Donaw,</hi> which lay below the Bridge, amongst which, the Ship wherein <hi>Hassan Bashaw</hi> and almost all the Turkish Grandees were got suncke in the Water, &amp; were there all drowned together, with the son of the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish Emperours Daughter. The Emperour being hereupon enraged, swore hee would revenge it, and caused the 24 of <hi>August,</hi> when he had wonne <hi>Sieseck,</hi> all the Men and Women which where therein to be cut in pieces, and throwne into the Water by <hi>Culpa,</hi> and dealt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther most inhumanely, both with Women and Children, a certain Moncke who thought to hide himselfe, he caused to be fleaed a live, cut in pieces, and so burnt: burning also all that was there, tooke likewise 500 Christians with him, to torture them in their captivity: hee caused also the peace with the German Emperour to be broken, and desired no longer Tribute of him; but would destroy his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey with fire and sword, he caused presently the Embassadour of the Emperour <hi>Rudolphus</hi> to be bound with Iron chaines, one of which was locked about his Necke, and the other about his feete, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed all the said Embassadors Servants in his presence to be murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and cutt in pieces; then he entred the feild, and wonn the Cittie <hi>Vespryn,</hi> after that the Christians had a long time defended the same, some escaping at a sally port, after they had set the Cittie on fier, to a place called <hi>Papa:</hi> afterwards hee wonne <hi>Palatta,</hi> but the Garrison (contrary to promise made) were all cut off: upon the 30 of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> hee cometh before <hi>Papa,</hi> out of which place two Hungarians
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205196:12"/> run over to the Turkes and discovered unto them all the secrets of the Citie so that the Governour yielded up the chiefe fortresse to the Turkish Emperour upon parole, provided that they might have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to march out; But asoone as hee with his poeple were without the gates both hee and all his people were cutt in pieces by the Turkes; But God raised againe other Enemyes against the Turkes, for the Persians and Georgians stood up against the grand <hi>Signiour</hi> by which meanes the Christians tooke the occasion to besiege <hi>Stoel-VVeissenburgh</hi> and the Turkes comming to the reliefe thereof, were courageously beaten, the Christians wonne <hi>Sabatga,</hi> which is a pass into <hi>Hungary,</hi> and leaving <hi>Stoel-VVeissenburg</hi> besieged, won <hi>Filleck,</hi> and upon the 11 of <hi>November</hi> againe, very stoutly beate the Turkes out of the feild, and afterwards tooke in <hi>Dregel, Palanoka, Samosko, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacko, Smolkyskow,</hi> and <hi>VVetskee.</hi> Anno 1594 were more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations made in <hi>Germany</hi> against the Turkes then ever before: the Duke <hi>Mathias</hi> was made Generall of the Leaguer; It happened that in the depth of Winter the Garrison of <hi>Comorra</hi> going out upon a partie, did intercept a turkish Bride, sitting upon a neatly trimmed turkish Waggon, with two turkish Boyes and an old Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame, who had order to carry the Bride (who was the Bashaw of <hi>Papans</hi> Daughter) to her Bridegroome; the Soldiers brake the Waggon in pieces, let the Beldame escape, but brought the Bride (who was very beautifull and aimable) and the two Boyes into <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morra:</hi> The Christians wonn also <hi>Novograde</hi> and <hi>Petryna;</hi> the 11 of <hi>July</hi> the Turkes wonn <hi>Dotis,</hi> and besieged <hi>Raab,</hi> which they (after much blood shed, and brave defence made) gott by treachery from the Count van <hi>Hardeck,</hi> who for the same was beheaded (and his hand with which hee had subscribed the agreement) chopt off; the Turkes having thus gotten the Key of the Romish Empire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seiged <hi>Comorra,</hi> in the meane time <hi>Amurath</hi> the Turkish Emperour upon the 8 of <hi>January</hi> dyed at <hi>Constantinople, Mahomet</hi> the 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg> suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in his place, who being a subtle Prince (assoone as hee was gotten upon the Throne, and knowing that the Prince of <hi>Transilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> (who was but newly marryed to the Lady <hi>Maria Christina</hi> of <hi>Austria</hi> the Daughter of the Arch-Duke <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Austria</hi>) had made a strong and neare Alliance with the Roman Emperour against
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:205196:12"/> the Turkes, and that those of <hi>Transylvania</hi> could do him much harme, wrote to this new marryed Prince, in very friendly manner, and promised to sett the Crowne of <hi>Hungary</hi> upon his head, telling him, that he could not beleeve that a Nation as his was, that had all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes received so many courtesies from the Turkes, could now so forsake their Benefactors; promised also to make him Generall over <hi>VVallachia</hi> and <hi>Moldavia;</hi> But all this was in vaine, the Prince of <hi>Transylvania</hi> remained faithfull to the house of <hi>Austria,</hi> and did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards beate the Turkes out of the feild: Afterwards the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans besieged <hi>Gran,</hi> lying upon the <hi>Donaw</hi> (who in the moneth of <hi>July</hi> saw by night a burning Rod in the Firmament, which appeared most fearfully like a bundle of branches) and suffered much trouble and losse in the said Siege: At last the Turke came with agreat force to releive <hi>Gran:</hi> whereas a Hungarian horseman came into the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Leaguer crying out aloude, <hi>Ho kill all Christians, kill all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians:</hi> The Generall <hi>Mansfeld</hi> hearing this, caused the Hungarian to be apprehended, and presently in his Bootes and Spurres to be hanged up: The Turkes indeed fell on very furiously, and to make themselves more outrageous in the attacque, had swallowed very much of a herbe they call <hi>Masla,</hi> which caused them to foame very much at the mouth: one of their Horsemen, who was behung round about with Gun powder (and thought to get into <hi>Gran,</hi> to the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of the besieged) being shott, and the powder catching fire, the Turke together with his Horse, in most fearfull manner flew up into the Ayre, and fell downe again in many pieces; in this fight the Turkes were beaten, and forced to flie, in so much, that <hi>Gran</hi> was upon the 25 of <hi>August</hi> forced to yeild, and the 24 of <hi>September Petrina</hi> also. The Prince of <hi>Transylvania</hi> did at the same time march out against the Turkes, and when he was come into the first Village in <hi>VVallachia,</hi> and had there placed his princely Pavillion, a very great Eagle came flying downe from a very high Rocke, and sett upon the Princes Tent, which the Princes Courtiers seeing, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently brought their Lord the message, who commanded that they should proffer the Eagle some meate, which the Eagle tooke, and did eate, and kept company with the Leaguer, and let herselfe be willingly taken, and was afterwards a long time fed and nourished in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205196:13"/> the Princes Court: upon the 15 of <hi>October</hi> the whole Leaguer beheld above the said Rocke in the East a most fearefull Comet; soon after hee puts the Turkes to flight, winneth <hi>St George, Tergovist,</hi> and <hi>Georea.</hi> Anno 1597 the Christians winn <hi>Totis.</hi> Anno 1599 the Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loones and French sell the strong fortresse <hi>Papa,</hi> and also <hi>Canisia</hi> to the Turkes. Anno 1600 they wonn <hi>Stoelweissenbourgh,</hi> and burnt the whole Citie, and with a Cannon shott beate in pieces the stone Monument, under which King <hi>Ladislaus,</hi> his Wife, and her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Mary</hi> lay buried, and dispoyled the Corps of all their Jewells, none of which were ever recovered or restored. Anno 1604 dieth the Turkish Emperour, his Successor required, that the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour should send him the usual Tribute, and if he desired Peace, that he must then renounce and desert <hi>VVallachia</hi> and <hi>Transylvania,</hi> and that hee in stead of them would give the Emperour <hi>Canisia</hi> and <hi>Erlan,</hi> the Emperour answered him, that <hi>Transylvania</hi> came to him by inheritance, but that he would treate with him about <hi>VVallachia;</hi> and that hee would likewise anihilate the Tribute either by treaty or contract: Then gott the Turkes <hi>Pest</hi> without blow or resistance, the Garrison through feare running away. At that time neare <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckeres,</hi> in <hi>Transylvania,</hi> hard by the Citie <hi>Sackmar,</hi> many persons of credit and reputation did by cleare daylight behold two <hi>Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sars</hi> (who seemed red as blood) riding on horsebacke, they had each of them a golden Crowne, with a little crosse upon their heads, and held each of them a Flagg (whereon was a red Rosse,) in their hands, which they trayled along the groūd; they afterwards rode to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Patrack,</hi> and over the same, as if it had been upon Ice, afterwards both together vanished away. Then the Turkes wonn <hi>Novigrade.</hi> The 9 of <hi>May</hi> the Tartars came before <hi>Newhausell</hi> (which is a City built by <hi>Mons Le Mot</hi> a Frenchman) and after they had suffered much miserie and greate famine they tooke the said Citie by agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Their Generals name was <hi>Han,</hi> and the Turkes would faine have bought <hi>Newhausel</hi> of him, but <hi>Han</hi> refused to do it, and dyed presently after. Anno 1606 was a Pea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for twenty yeares concluded: betweene the Roman and Turkish Emperour, beginning the first of <hi>January</hi> 1607; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n was the Citie of <hi>Newhausell</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the 11 of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> again surrendered to the Emperour. Hereupon the Emperour
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:205196:13"/>
               <hi>Mathias</hi> was in the yeare 1607 and 1608 crowned King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and most magnificently received in all his hereditary lands, and was marryed unto <hi>Anna</hi> Queen of <hi>Hungaria</hi> and <hi>Bohemia.</hi> And was Anno 1612 at <hi>Franckford</hi> crowned King of the Romans, in so much, that every where throughout the whole Empire, at that time no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Joy and rejoycing was seene or heard, for this Emperour being the Sonn of <hi>Maximilian,</hi> was a courteous and wise Man, and when he was but 20 yeare old, was Elected Gouvernour of the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands.</hi> Anno 1577 he came over to <hi>Brussel,</hi> and made <hi>VVilliam</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to be his deputy Lieutenant: and thence forward the Emperour <hi>Mathias</hi> did reigne very wisely. Then was <hi>Aken</hi> by malice of the Romans, and order of the Emperour taken in, and the <hi>Protestants</hi> were banished from thence. <hi>Mulheim</hi> which had been with so great charges built, was demolished. At that time the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and Turkish Emperours made a cessation for 20 yeares. The <hi>Protestants</hi> intending to celebrate the <hi>Jubily yeare,</hi> from <hi>Luthers</hi> time were in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and other Imperiall Countryes hindered to do the same, by reason whereof, certaine Lords were at <hi>Prague</hi> throwne out of the Windows. The Prince Electour of <hi>Saxony</hi> takes Armes against these proceedings: In the meane time the Emperour <hi>Mathias</hi> having banished <hi>Mansfeld,</hi> grew dayly weaker, and being 62 yeares old, (having reigned 9 yeares) was encountered with a very violent sicknesse, whereof hee dyed; Anno 1609 <hi>Ferdinandus</hi> Arch-Duke of <hi>Austria</hi> was Elected Emperour, and Crowned at <hi>Franckford,</hi> hee was the Son of the Arch-Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Albrecht</hi> Duke of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> The Empire was in great discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent about this election, and those of <hi>Bohemia</hi> rebelling, drove the <hi>Iesuites</hi> out of the Kingdome; and made <hi>Frederick Paltzgrave</hi> of the <hi>Rhine</hi> their King: The other Prince Electors being hereupon very discontented, held a dyet or Councell at <hi>Regensburgh:</hi> But King <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> writing to the other Prince Electors, caused himselfe to be Crowned King at <hi>Prague:</hi> And the Empire hereupon falling into va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance and discord, <hi>Bethelem Gabor</hi> Prince of <hi>Transylvania</hi> cometh downe, &amp; tooke the great Citie of <hi>Presburgh</hi> from the Emperour, and corresponding with those of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> tooke in the meane time o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, and aspired to the Crown of <hi>Hungary,</hi> which hee obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205196:14"/> but never suffered the same to be put upon his head, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore never bore other title then Prince of <hi>Hungary.</hi> Anno 1620 the Germans, for the free exercise of either Religion, kept a Couneell or Synod at <hi>Norenbourgh,</hi> where <hi>Frederick</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and also at <hi>VVurtsburgh:</hi> in the interim those of <hi>Austria,</hi> yea the Emperour himselfe grew weake, and the Count of <hi>Boucquoy</hi> becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing necessitous, and seeing great likelyhood, that the <hi>Bohemians</hi> would get the mastery, retired into <hi>Moravia,</hi> in the meane time, the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> by publike Heralds and Proclamations, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth void the Election of the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> shewing his owne lawfull proprietie and right to the Crowne, yet the <hi>Bohemians</hi> rested very well contented with their King <hi>Frederick;</hi> but many were dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, because he too speedily caused the Altar, and other Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Ornaments in the Emperours Chappell, to be broken in pieces: while <hi>Moravia, Silesia</hi> and <hi>Lawfints</hi> in the meane time treate for their security: In the interim, <hi>Don Balthazar Macadas,</hi> with an Army of Polanders and Cossacks, falleth into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> making miserable havocke there amongst the <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Hussars.</hi> In a Dyet at <hi>Mulhuysen</hi> endeavour was used, to perswade King <hi>Fredrick</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist and renounce the <hi>Bohemian</hi> Crowne, but <hi>Frederick</hi> was of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, the election belonged neither to the Emperour, nor the Princes but onely to the Cities and Burgesses of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> who also declared his eldest Son <hi>Frederick</hi> to be his Successor in the Kingdome: in the meane time the Emperour strengthens himselfe with the <hi>Pope, Spaine, Inspruch, Poland</hi> and others; and the Duke <hi>Maximilian</hi> of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> entreth with an Army into feild, and <hi>Iohn George</hi> with an other, they both being jealous of the good Successe of the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and <hi>Spinola</hi> cometh also out of the Netherlands thither, and upon the 8 of <hi>November</hi> 1620, they beate the King out of the feild, nere <hi>VVitten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergh</hi> by <hi>Prague,</hi> where the Crowne of <hi>Bohemia</hi> fell to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: and King <hi>Frederick</hi> fled with his Queene and Children to the Netherlands. In the like manner was <hi>Moravia</hi> by <hi>Bucquoy</hi> also made subject, but when he came before the fortresse <hi>Newhausel,</hi> he was fallen upon by the Hungarians, and got 16 wounds. At which time <hi>Bethelem Gabor</hi> gave over by an agreement at <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>clausburgh,</hi> the Crowne of <hi>Hungary</hi> to the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> yet neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205196:14"/> preserving many rights for himselfe together with the Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palaty's of <hi>Oppelan</hi> and <hi>Ratibor,</hi> and likewise the title of Prince of the Empire. Now the Emperour having his hands free, began to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secute the Protestant Ministers, and caused their Bookes to be burnt: chasing many Teachers and Schoolmasters out of the hereditary Imperiall Countryes, whereupon the Hungarians, anno 1624 made an agreement with <hi>Bethelem Gabor.</hi> Anno 1625 the Emperour made a truce of 12 yeares with the Turkes. And 1627 traveling to <hi>Prague,</hi> caused the Empress to be crowned Queene of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and his Son <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg> King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi> Anno 1631 the Swedes invaded <hi>Germany,</hi> destroying the whole Empire, and in several Battles, beate many thousands of the Imperialists, till the yeare 1634, the Ballance Battle betweene the Swedes and the Emperour was fought before <hi>Nordlingen: Prague</hi> being besieged and halfe wonn. Anno 1637 the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the 2d dyed at <hi>Vienna,</hi> and his Son <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the 3<seg rend="sup">d</seg> presently tooke the Government upon him: And anno 1638 <hi>Mariade Medicis</hi> the Queene Mother came out of <hi>Braband</hi> to <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterdam.</hi> Anno 1648 was the peace concluded at <hi>Munster,</hi> in the interim many small and almost inconsiderable things, like to that of <hi>Wallenstein,</hi> fell out in the Empire. Anno 1642 the Swedes tooke <hi>Olmits</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> but the Peace of <hi>Munster</hi> maketh every one glad, whole <hi>Germany</hi> hopeth for Joye, and those who had fled away, returned againe to their Vineyards, yet nevertheless the <hi>Saxon</hi> could not endure any Papists, nor the Emperour Protestants, but the Prince <hi>Palatin</hi> (now the eighth Elector) doth permit every one: In the meane time the Turkes waging Warr with the <hi>Venetians,</hi> take <hi>Canea</hi> in <hi>Candia,</hi> and would faine have taken all the <hi>Islands</hi> of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chipelago;</hi> but finding themselves over matched at Sea, did in the yeare 1663 send forth a great Army by land, against <hi>Austria,</hi> to take his revenge upon the Germans: the now present Emperour <hi>Leopold</hi> the 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg> being delayed with hope, and now having sent his Embassadours, the <hi>Baron de Goes</hi> and <hi>Doctor Pearle,</hi> to <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> began to perceive, that all was but meere deceipt, and that if he tooke not greater care, they would endeavour to wring the Keys of <hi>Austria</hi> out of his hands: the Turke on the other side collogued with the said Embassadours in <hi>Turkey,</hi> as if they had been their best friends, sending out a report to France, and other Christian Courts,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:205196:15"/> as if they were already newly agreed with the German Emperour: in the meane time they sent from all places under the Prime <hi>Visier</hi> to <hi>Belgrada, Canise,</hi> and <hi>Offen</hi> their Soldiers by 3, 4, and 500 together, and also much Cannon and Ammunition, to the Generall Rande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, preparing mighty Magazines and stores of Provisions, to which end they before hand cruelly forced the Countrey-people, both in <hi>Transylvania</hi> and other places, that they neither might nor should bring their Catle to any other, then those places to market: The Count <hi>Seryn</hi> as a true friend to Germany, forewarned the Emperour most of all, and required assistance, for the defence of his Fortress, which lyeth upon the borders of <hi>Austria,</hi> as a Wall to Christendome, in which Countrey his Predecessours and family hath for several hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares been knowne, and acknowledged for faithfull Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions to <hi>Europe:</hi> He having been informed, that the Turkes were in <hi>April</hi> 1663 already assembled at <hi>Canise,</hi> with 1500 Waggons (each Waggon with 3 Horses) which were onely the train of the <hi>Janisaries.</hi> And <hi>Transylvania</hi> was now taxed and racked by the Turkes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though their Prince <hi>Abafti</hi> had promised the Inhabitants better dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, yet were forced thereunto by <hi>Aly Bashaw,</hi> who governed severely. The Emperour being yet but young, and perceiving him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe thus sore menaced with great calamities, knew not from which side the great storme was to be expected. The Turkes (as they said) had seene this following Prodigie in the Firmament, above their frontiers against Christendome, and did prognosticate the same, as a forerunner of good fortune.</p>
            <figure/>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:205196:15"/>
            <p> But they mocked so long therewith in <hi>Austria</hi> till God did also about <hi>Mairen</hi> and <hi>Silesia,</hi> but especially about <hi>Austria,</hi> shew a Comet, or strange Starr in the Firmament, which spread its selfe over <hi>Moravia,</hi> a certain Messenger of Gods most dreadfull wrath, for the Sinnes of mankinde: The Jesuites in <hi>Olmitz,</hi> the cheife Cittie of <hi>Moravia,</hi> did thus decipher this Comet, as they saw the same, upon the 8, 9, 10, 11, and 12, dayes of <hi>February</hi> 1662, being a great Comet of a fiery colour, but short in its appearance, standing upon the necke of the Eagle, and upon one of his winges.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Whereupon many have made very probable prognostications. This unusual Starr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as also seen in the Netherlands, by the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> Astronomers, but the nearer the same came to <hi>Holland,</hi> the more it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205196:16"/> lost its Station, and at length came to nothing. On the other side the Protestants States in <hi>Hungary,</hi> rose against the Romanists in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stria,</hi> asking againe the Churches, which had been taken from them, restablishment of their Priviledges, and freedome of Religion, to which the Imperial Court would not listen, in so much, that there was a suspition, that the <hi>Hungarians</hi> (as here tofore) would submit and receive the Turkes, and on the other side the Emperour was jealous, that (because of certain discontents happened betweene the French King, and the Duke of <hi>Loraine,</hi> probably the King might have a designe against <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> and consequently upon <hi>Germany,</hi> and the rather, because he seemed to have made a League with seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Princes upon the <hi>Rhine;</hi> moreover there was a dyet or assembly convened at <hi>Regensburgh,</hi> to put a stop to the Turkes; But there were more expences thereby charged upon <hi>Europe,</hi> then proffit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounded to Christendome, but no body would acknowledge the Emperour, until all Priviledges and pretenses were satisfied, <hi>and then they would talke of giving of money.</hi> The Turkes on the other side perceiving the difference betweene the German Princes: the Warr menaced betweene the French and the Pope: the jealosie of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Kings of each other; And <hi>Poland</hi> but now hardly freed from the slavery of the Warr, and threatened with a new <hi>Sedem Bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> by the Muscovites: That the Cossackes were inclined to the Turkish Court: did also induce or perswade all the Tartars, and other his wilde Tributaires, who dwell on the <hi>Euxine</hi> Seas northwards, and toward <hi>Japan,</hi> as Slaves to stand up for him, and to helpe to subdue the Germans (whom the Mahometan Monarch called a wicked people) to establish his Throne, and accordingly hee said in this following manner (in his most unfashionable heathenish speech) <hi>That he according to the old prophecy, to that effect foretold many yeares since, would make the Cathedrall Church, or Dome of the City of Colen upon the Rhine, to be a Stable for his Horses:</hi> And thus heat last in the yeare 1663, caused his Bashaw to march from <hi>Offen</hi> by <hi>Sakata</hi> with 140000▪ Turkes, and all sorts of other Nations o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Donaw,</hi> where at first his Ship-Bridge broke; but the same being again repaired, being also assisted by the Countrey people, they with 120 pieces of ordinance, and all things else got over, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205196:16"/> imediatly sent before them a body of 40000 the best armed Soldiers, and for a terrour to all the Inhabitants of <hi>Austria,</hi> sent to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of <hi>Germany</hi> this arrogant and blasphemous Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the great commanding God in Heaven, how much more a God upon Earth, the greatest and allmightiest Emperour, an invincible &amp; ruling King on earth, from the rising of the Sun to the setting thereof; Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and Sultan of</hi> Babylon; <hi>Duke of the noble familie in</hi> Media <hi>and</hi> Armenia, <hi>a borne Prince and Lord of the drye VVilderness till beyond the Hills: A great helper of both Gods,</hi> Mahomet <hi>and</hi> Luna, <hi>Victor and Triumpher at</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>a Lord preserver and Protector of the Sepulcher of the crucified God; A destroyer, and for ever a sworne Enemy to Christendome, and of all those who call themselves Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians. VVee signify to you Emperour, a petty King in</hi> Hungary <hi>and</hi> Bohemia, <hi>to you and all your Princes and Lords, and also to all and every your Subjects, to the Pope, and Cardinall Bishops and Natives; And wee sweare unto you that wee by election of our Throne, denounce and will execute upon you all mischeifs and destructions in your whole Land; and let you assuredly know, that wee will come and visit you with thirteene Kingly Nations, consisting of more then 100000, both Horse and foot, Turkes with Turkish armes, and with the utmost forces as good and able as you ever heard or saw, and wee intend, by our force of Armes, your Citties, and all those who are therein, and especially▪ your Pallace and Court, with all your helpers and assistors, to burne, plunder, murther and destroy, and put you to the most shamefullest death, which wee can thinke or imagin, and cause your Christians our prisoners to be strangled, and as Doggs to be kept in miserable and everlasting captivitie, and set up your Children as a prey of Carcasses in the open fields; wee will cause the VVomen with child, with the Infants in their Mothers wombes as Doggs to be killed and put to death, and the Christians to be a shame and mocking stocke, wee doe also intend by force to depose thee Emperour, with those few Countreyes thou hast from thy Empire by Sword and force of warr, and also to oppresse and destroy the Keyes and seat of Rome, and also the Golden Scepter, and wee will trye if your Crucified Jesus (whom you and yours say lives) can helpe you as hee hath holpen your Legates: which wee will
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205196:17"/> not take into our beleife; neither can or may wee beleeve or heare such incomprehensible things, as that hee hath power to helpe, because hee is long time since dead; and could not helpe himselfe, because wee for several hundred yeares have had the Dominion of his Countrey and his Doctrine in our Empire; This wee would let you know to the intent, thou poore little King with all thy assistants may daily and every minute take notice thereof, even as thou also verily in a short time shall finde and feele.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given in our mightie Fortresse, and cheife Citie <hi>Constantinople,</hi> (which our Predecessors have by force of VVarr taken from you, and miserably chased away both VVomen and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and will keepe the same according to our will to the last, to the shame of the Christians) in <date>the 23 yeare of our nativity, and in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> yeare of our now mighty Empire.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This bitter and Antichristian Letter was presently put into exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, by the destruction of many Townes &amp; Villages in <hi>Hungary,</hi> after that they in <hi>August</hi> last, had first of all besieged the Fortress called <hi>Vesprin,</hi> where they missed their aime, by reason that the great Cannon and vigillancy of the Count <hi>Seryn</hi> rowsed them away; by which meanes the <hi>Bashaw</hi> and the rest of the Turks councell of Warr resolved to besiege some considerable place over the <hi>Donaw;</hi> upon the 11 of <hi>August</hi> 1663 they fall upon the famous Fortress of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hausell,</hi> which lyeth in a Morasse, in which Count <hi>Forgats</hi> an Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garian had the Command, who but lately before was unfortunatly beaten by the Turkes, in their passage over the <hi>Donaw;</hi> they first stormed the Cittie neare the Vienna Towre, and made their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters round about the same, namely on the Austrian side on the right hand, lay with his quarter <hi>Becho Bashaw Grand Visier</hi> of <hi>Offen,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nine Batteries, of three demy Cannon, and five whole Cannon, on the left side of <hi>Newhausell,</hi> had <hi>Aly Bashaw</hi> his quarter, with two Faulcons, and two demy Cannons, and several small pieces: at the Tower of <hi>Gran</hi> the <hi>Bashaw Captain</hi> had his quarter with 3 Faulcons:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:205196:17"/> The fourth quarter lay on the left hand of the above mentioned, under the Command of the <hi>Janisaries, Agasay,</hi> with one Falcon and two demy Cannons, having round about the Fortresse Batteries, at the end of euery fifty paces. Now at that time those of <hi>Moravia</hi> began first to see the wrath of God, and the certainty of his messen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the Comet here before mentioned, which appeared in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens: And it was also well known to those in the Countrey, in the Village <hi>Dillein,</hi> lying a quarter of a mile from <hi>Schomnits,</hi> one of the mountain Citties, upon the fourteeneth of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1663, a Sowe brought forth a Monster, the upper part thereof had wholy the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblance of a Woman, with faire and long curled haire, which hung over the eyes, and had a great bunch like a plume of Feathers upon the head; altogether of the same fashion as the prowd Ladyes in <hi>Moravia</hi> and <hi>Hungary</hi> used to wear the same year; on the feet of this young Swine were seene the new fashioned horne shooes, and other figures of pride. And in the Imperiall Citie <hi>Vienna,</hi> by a small Rocket of wild fire, which fell downe upon a Stable where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was much Haye, many Houses were turned into ashes; which was a warning piece: the Turkes (who all knew to make use of occasions) had in their comming the Hungarians to be their friends; which people consisting of many Protestants, both Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists, Lutherans, and others, were by the rage of the Jesuites depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved both of the freedome of their Conscience and use of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; these Hungarians, seeing that that the Romish Clergy were so much regarded in the Imperiall Court, and that they (as Beggars) were alwayes put off with a slight answer, did afterwards more and more turne themselves to the Turkes who having now mastered <hi>VVaradin</hi> and <hi>Transilvania</hi> let the People remaine in the Countrey, taking a civil Tribute, and suffered each to enjoye his Conscience and Religion without any incumbrances; they did therefore think by reason that the Emperour could not defend <hi>Transylvania</hi> against the Turkes, (and that the storme would fall upon <hi>Hungary</hi>) that it was better to receive a Prince who could defend them, and give them liberty of Conscience, then one who wanted power, and seemed to force them in their Conscience. The Emperour well perceiving which way the tide would turne, appeared presently in a Dyet or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:205196:18"/> Councell at <hi>Presbourgh;</hi> where the Councell-chamber oftentimes shooke with many high words and protestations, yet in vaine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out pacifying any discontents, for the Hungarians told him plainly, that they could not assist, unless their Priviledges and Churches were restored as in former time; whereunto the Romish Ecclesiasticks were not inclined: And by this meanes the Turkes invaded <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia,</hi> to the great astonishment and distruction of many thousand Soules, who were thereby slaine, and carried into captivity. The Tartars had one body of 15000 Horsemen, and the Turkes two bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of 40000 men, and 36000 which they kept on the other side of the <hi>Donaw,</hi> and whilst they were busie in bringing the Cannon before <hi>Newhausell;</hi> these bodyes came into severall places, burning <hi>Shaumey</hi> and <hi>Gran,</hi> and the faire and pleasant <hi>Beckenso:</hi> The Tartars in the meane while get over the Water called the <hi>VVaag,</hi> where one <hi>Elias Thasie</hi> an Hungarian with some Troopes lay, for defence, but hee seeing them come, did not expect nor stay for the Enemy, but deserted the same, and most shamefully rann away. The Tartars comming into the Mountainous places, got great booty by their plundering <hi>St George, Tesing</hi> and <hi>Derduke,</hi> and from thence they come into <hi>Moravia,</hi> in somuch, that the Jesuits at <hi>Olmits</hi> could see by day and by night many fires of those Villages, which they every night turned into ashes; the Tartars burned also the faire Cities of <hi>Passing, Thouron, Moron,</hi> and <hi>Ʋrystalein,</hi> and in <hi>Moravia</hi> more then 60 Townes and Villages, cutting in pieces many old People and young Children, and carrying away many thousands of young men and Women into captivity to be sould, whom they sent into chaynes to Tartary and Turkey: These miserable Captives they carry to both their Marketts, and looke both Man and Woman in the mouth and in the teeth, (as they doe the Horses in the Netherlands) how old they are, which accordingly are bought at high or low prices: now was every one afraid (as they had cause,) of this barbarous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion; The Citie <hi>Presburgh</hi> was overfilled with people, who fled away, in somuch, that from thence were presently sent away into <hi>Austria</hi> and <hi>Bavaria,</hi> all the Women and Children; for this Citie which was but provided only for an encounter, (yet fortified with a Castle) saw no possibillity of keeping out the Turkes by maine
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:205196:18"/> force; yea at <hi>Vienna</hi> it selfe, people without number, which were fled, lay before the Gates and Bridge, which could not be let in, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the said Bridges by so much thronging of flying Waggons, Cartes, Houses, and people, was broken downe: The misery of these people was very great, one telling that as hee fled, hee saw by the way such and such noble Mans Houses, Castles, pleasure Houses and Villages on fire, further that he had seen by the way, old Men, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Lords and others cut in pieces and stripped, the one whole and the other halfe plundered, some fallen upon and murthered, lying under wheeles of Carts and Waggons, some as they were setting at table, others in their Beds, and as they were asleepe, were fallen upon and murthered: They were the happiest, who flying day and night could in time escape with their lives, leaving behinde them the rich Copper mines, which are by <hi>Newhausell,</hi> and the greene Water which falls there (which is well kowne to Paynters) also the rare Bathes of <hi>Missia</hi> and <hi>Crauschin,</hi> and the healthfull warme spring lying on the water <hi>VVaag,</hi> together with the delicious Carpes and other well tasted Fish in the River <hi>Tibisen,</hi> and forgetting the trade of the Townes and Hills, the bleatings of the multitudes of Sheepe, the gathering of Wooll, and making of the most renowned Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Cloathes, neither could now the searchers of Nature have time to trouble themselves to enquire, what sort of Poyson lyes hid in a place of the earth, by the Hills of <hi>Newhausell,</hi> that whatsoever Bird flieth over the same dyeth, or else wherefore the water of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine neare <hi>Leewa,</hi> assoone as it springeth out turneth into Stone, or why the water of the Fountaine <hi>Smolints</hi> consumeth Iron, and caused a horseshooe which hade been therin 24 houres to be as soft as mud. That the Inhabitans make Copper of Cypres, And why Vitriol of the flower of Copper, and Salte Fountains growe. There were now other things to thinke of, and great feare. And yet could not the German Deputyes at <hi>Regensburgh</hi> in the Diet, or Councel agree to assist the Emperour: some Princes sent many small Troopes but these came so slowly on, as the <hi>Donaw</hi> floweth in the heate of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer hardly knowing whether to runn backward or forwards: on the other side all sortes of Antichristian Enemys flowed abundantly in the Emperours hereditary Countryes, beholding now before
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:205196:19"/> them a Treasure of rich Prey left open to them. The Son of the Great <hi>Cham</hi> of <hi>Tartary</hi> came himselfe, with 163 Standards into <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres</hi> (being as was beleeved) thereunto induced by the approaching Booty. The <hi>Weywooda</hi> of <hi>Wallachia,</hi> with a Company of 600 tall fellows with red Coates about him for his Guard, armed only with Bowes and Arrows, otherwise so slightly and pitifully moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted like unto unarmed Grasshoppers, lame horses, and halting Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers: These and the <hi>Bashaw</hi> of <hi>Erlan,</hi> came also together, and went to <hi>Pest</hi> over the <hi>Donaw</hi> towards <hi>Lewents,</hi> and the Mountain Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: where these poore people having no Mills to grinde, were forced to eate their Corne greene, but many by weariness and famine fell downe, by the high way, which by reason of the great raine were become very wet: they had in their Leaguer the greatest Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish Cannon drawne by 70 Buffels or Oxen, which shot a 96 pound Bullet; this piece broke, and killed many <hi>Janisaries</hi> with the blow, yet neverthelesse the cruell Barbarians, when they came into <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia,</hi> beate and destroyed foure Regiments of Croatian Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons, of which not ten Men escaped, and also the Regiment of <hi>Scharles,</hi> and hee himselfe mortally wounded; The Holsteiners beate themselves through them, those of <hi>Brym</hi> and <hi>Moravia</hi> saw these Heathens demaund the surrender of a principal Passe: and in the meane time almost all living thereabouts sought protection within their strong Walls and Gates. They also in the same time saw <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagelo Brokowits</hi> and <hi>Ostrowa</hi> stand all of a flame, the passage to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wits, Zaromits</hi> and <hi>Paskowits,</hi> would hardly be secured by the felling of the Trees: The Prince of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uthen,</hi> and Count <hi>Copperdofestein</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sooke their Castles and Countrey, and broke off the Bridges behind them, and came with their Ladyes into <hi>Brin: Hallits, Gubsan, Strafius, Wesel, Green</hi> and <hi>Staints</hi> were also seen all on fire, Another part of the Tartars, who broke into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> fell upon <hi>Kottenburgh,</hi> lying a League from <hi>Prague,</hi> into the Cloister of the Nunnes, which they throughly plundered, and tooke most of the Nunnes with them, and cut of the breasts off some of them; an Earle sitting at the Table, leapt out at the Window and fled; but the Nunnes were all of them car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried captives out of the Cloyster; by reason hereof, the old Empress fled from <hi>Vienna</hi> to <hi>Lints.</hi> Every fifth man in <hi>Austria</hi> was enrolled,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205196:19"/> the Imperiall Treasure was hudled up together, <hi>Brestaw</hi> in <hi>Silesia</hi> mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters Soldiers: the Pesants are sent into the Hills and Mountaines to destroy and spoyle the Trees and Highwayes, the deare Corne har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest, yarne, trade and commerce were all neglected, all people were in confusion. In the meane time, the Turkes before <hi>Newhausell</hi> use their utmost force (and being taught by those, that had seene the same done in <hi>Europe</hi>) drained the Water of the <hi>Nap</hi> in the Moras out, though their great shott did little harme to those within, who tooke an oath to defend the same place to the utmost: in the interim the Imperiall Generall, Count <hi>Montecuculli</hi> lay sicke of a fevor at <hi>Presburgh:</hi> and the Hungarian Crown was for security carried out of that Cittie; Neither did the Turks escape free, one of their Visiers was before <hi>Newhausell</hi> shot through his side, many of the beleague<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers were killed, and the Grand <hi>Ʋisier</hi> of <hi>Offen</hi> grew extream sicke; who till now had detained with him, the Emperours Embassador, the Baron <hi>de Goes,</hi> to the end he might take notice, what power and forces the Turkish Emperour had there: the same <hi>de Goes</hi> had a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confessor, who was a great Chymist and Philosopher, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed himselfe to cure the <hi>Ʋisier,</hi> which tooke so good effect, that the <hi>Visier</hi> esteemed him as a Prophet or Saint, and would not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore suffer this father Confessor to goe from him. On the other side there came news to <hi>Prague</hi> that about the same time, the Turkish Emperour understanding that the Count <hi>Seryn,</hi> in <hi>Vespryn</hi> had beaten off the Turkish Leaguer, and would apparently by his great courage performe some notable Exploit, by invading of <hi>Turkey,</hi> caused a Cabinet to be presented to him, full (as the bearer hereof, who was a Turke said) of precious Stones; the Count <hi>Seryin</hi> well knowing the Turkish deceipts and faire wordes, was suspitious thereof; and that there was some treachery therein, yet he nevertheless resolved as a gratuity for this present, to release a Turke, who was a person of great quallity, and his Prisoner; desiring that the said released Turke before his departure should open the said Cabinet, which he doing, there came five shott or Bullets out of it, with which hee being wounded fell downe dead upon the ground, whereupon the Count <hi>Seryn</hi> perceiving the said treachery, fell with a considerable force in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Turkey,</hi> and having killed many Turkes, returned with great
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:205196:20"/> Booty into his Fortress, hereupon it was reported that the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians were agreed with this Count, and that they with thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Men were ready to advance, for his assistance against the Turkes, but the same not yet Succeeding, those of <hi>Newhausell</hi> having been wearyed and spent almost sixs weeke space, and seeing also that there was such negligence to assist them, began to grow faint, the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians who were there within, hating the Austrians, opposed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves against their Commander <hi>Forgats,</hi> it was said by many that he and the Germans were willing to fight; But his enemyes say he having correspondence with the Turks, did upon the 27 of <hi>September</hi> (when there was an intention to releive the place) sell the same for 60000 Duckets; for certain it is that it was to the great griefe of the Emperour and shame of the Hungarians, the selfe same day deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by agreement over to the Turkes, notwithstanding there was no want within the place, but well provided for a long time, and also with 130 piece of Cannon; there marched out 3500 Men to <hi>Comorra;</hi> The Turks were glad of this Victory, and gave every Hungarian who would stay within a Ducket, the same they also promised to the Countrey people in the Mountains, which well pleased those people, in somuch that in a short time a further invasion of the Turkes is to be expected: for the Austrians did much suspect strange Nations, who profferd their assistance against the Turks; There is a report that France proffered 12000, and the mutinous Polander would advance with 7000 Men, if there were money to pay them; also Swethland and Denmarke did offer to do their indeavors: But were not accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, not withstanding, <hi>Austria, Bohemia, Sylesia,</hi> and <hi>Moravia</hi> lay now quite open to the Turkes, and that the Kingdome of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia,</hi> might be in a manner said to be totally▪ lost: God preserve the neighbouring places, and divert the haughtiness and selfe ends of the German Princes, the differences, discontents, and superfluous char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, in their pompous Dyets and Councels, The persecutions and divisions of the Christians (who being in <hi>Turkey,</hi> are all of one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) and the miseries of the German Empire, and that for <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> sake, who (for a time but not alwayes) in former times by the Jewes and Infidels, and also now at present suffered, and suffereth himselfe to be martred and mocked: But like as the Jewes since the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:205196:20"/> suffering of our <hi>Jesus,</hi> have missed their King, the same God will also in his due time finde out the Mahometans as well as the Jewes, and these worldly powers who threaten the God of heaven, whose judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment must be left alone, to that great God, whom the Hebrews call <hi>Jehova,</hi> the Greeks <hi>Theos,</hi> the Latins <hi>Deus,</hi> and the common people the <hi>Almighty God.</hi> Now this persecuted <hi>Jesus</hi> our Saviour (to whom the judgement at the last day is given over) who can thus suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer these Sarasens, who (as the Giants in <hi>Ovid,</hi>) like Children threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to wage Warr against Heaven, with the Mountains of their owne inventions, with their owne strength, notwithstanding that their life is short here, their power so small as their pride, whom Heaven cannot endure, is great shall sufficiently be manifested at last.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="supplement">
            <head>A <hi>SƲPPLEMENT</hi> To the Description of the Warrs in <hi>Hungary.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O yield some speculation to the considerate Reader, wee will give some demonstractions or animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, upon the Mapp or Card of Land, hereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed; beginning on the right hand with the Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>Transylvania,</hi> near the water <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eskeres,</hi> where is to be seen the chief Cittie <hi>VVaradyn,</hi> populous, lying in the Valley, but fortified after the old fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion, with some new fortifications, yet did nevertheless fall in part to the Turks share, because they by treachery made the Emperour of <hi>Germany</hi> beleeve, that their forces tended no further then to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablishing of a good Policy or Goverment in <hi>Transylvania,</hi> in the meane time <hi>Ragotski</hi> (the deceased Protestant) his Widdow (who was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Romanist) with a Son endeavored to preserve themselves in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205196:21"/> safety by flying, from one place to another: next you may see <hi>Tockay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which is a well built Castle, situated betweene the <hi>Bedroch,</hi> and the <hi>Rivoulus,</hi> (like <hi>Schenkenschans</hi> in the Netherlands) with convenient Bulwarks and Walls, which by the passage of the <hi>Joe</hi> have oftentimes suffered great dammage: Betweene <hi>VVassen</hi> and <hi>Satwan</hi> flow two Rivers or Torrents, called <hi>Genges</hi> and <hi>Salwitza,</hi> these at length fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Theis</hi> neare the Citie and Fortress called <hi>Solnock▪</hi> which is defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, (though not with large) yet with strong Walls, guarded at the points with a strong and well built Castle, separated in two parts (as <hi>Mastricht</hi> from <hi>VVaert</hi>) by a moat-bridge, environed with low Lands: you may also see springing out of the foremost <hi>Carpatish</hi> Mountaines the Water or River called the <hi>Tarsa,</hi> running over be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Eycrias,</hi> where it dischargeth it selfe into the water called the <hi>Hawat,</hi> where not farr from the foremost Mountaines <hi>Cresma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kuta</hi> the Citie <hi>Cassovia</hi> is situated, which is well built full of Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, and fortified with Walls and Bullwarks, on the other side of the <hi>Theys</hi> toward the frontiers of <hi>Transylvania,</hi> may you behold the faire Castles and Fortresses, called the <hi>Nagkalo, Kisko,</hi> and others there being; from thence to the <hi>Donaw</hi> almost no considerable place of strength, save onely <hi>St Nicholas</hi> and <hi>Buerten,</hi> upon an arme of the <hi>Donaw;</hi> you may see the Fortress <hi>Comorra,</hi> being a brave strength or defence to Christendome, lying upon the streame like an Island for severall Leagues in length and breath, the Inhabitants thereabouts call this strength or Fortress (as an accustomed name) their <hi>Defender,</hi> as concerning the Fortress it selfe, those who have taken a serious view say that it lyeth upon the lowermost part of this said Island, the Citie which lyeth neare thereunto is not of much concernment, they have a brave Castle, Tower and a Bridge over the <hi>Donaw,</hi> a Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Preaching-house, Hungarian Churches, Block-houses and Lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kills: The Fortress <hi>Raab</hi> which lyeth next thereunto, taketh its name more from the water <hi>Raab,</hi> wich runneth along there, then from the <hi>Donaw</hi> which also runneth there along: This place seperateth <hi>Austria</hi> from <hi>Hungary,</hi> here are also German and Hungarian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Castles, Townes, Suburbs, and other places, which are most of them ruined, and do lie wast <hi>Comorra</hi> in the middle near the <hi>Donaw:</hi> three leagues from thence, lyeth upon the <hi>Martins</hi> Hills, which reat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:205196:21"/> to the Clowdes) the Cloyster which yet is preserved onely with a fence of wood or garden pales: but southwards you may see in the Mapp <hi>Papa,</hi> situated by a great Dike, having only Turnepikes and a Wall to free them from any enterprise, with which the Castle also is defended: To the Eastward you may see <hi>Dotis</hi> which like to the above mentioned situated upon very high Hills, but a League from the <hi>Donaw,</hi> there is now nothing but a Castle, the Citie being long since ruined, not far from the Citie <hi>Moates</hi> are seen certain very high Hills, out of which they hew white Marble, the which Hills by their hight have alwayes been hurtfull to the said Castle, above upon the same do still stand an ancient Cloyster. The Turkes and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians have there their warme Bathes, and especially burying places: Not far from thence, upon the <hi>Donaw</hi> you may see <hi>Strigonium</hi> or <hi>Gran,</hi> which are four Cities, one upon the Hill; and two on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther side in the Champaine Countrey which are won and miserably ruined by the Turkes: neare thereunto you may see <hi>Vizegrades,</hi> a Castle and a little City, which was heretofore a place of pleasure of the Kings of <hi>Hungary;</hi> King <hi>Mathias</hi> did cause to be here built, many pleasure Gardens, Houses, Walkes, and Halls, of Marblestone and rich Wood. Then you runn along the <hi>Donaw</hi> to <hi>Offen, Buda</hi> or <hi>Pest,</hi> which the Turkes anno 1519 wonn from the Christians, and do ever since keepe in their possession, by which wee see that the Turkes by their unity, to the ignominy of the Romanist do more, and more establish themselves against the Christians, this Citie lyeth very pleasantly on both sides of the <hi>Donaw,</hi> and is well fortified, and hath also a Block-house upon the hill, a little without the great old Citie: from thence you may come over that Countrey to <hi>Vesprin,</hi> which is an ancient Episcopall Citie situated upon the River called the <hi>Sarwu,</hi> it lyeth upon a high hill, and hath its name from the white springing Fountaines: The lower Citie at present is of little consideration, but whatsoever is above upon the Hill, which goeth finely up, and on all sides sheweth its selfe very compleatly, comprehending with the Castle, the one within the other, are of strong defence, from thence you come to <hi>Pallota,</hi> being a Castle with double Moates, walled and foure Schonses, defended with Turne-pikes against any assault: Then if you turne your selfe to lower <hi>Hungary,</hi> you may finde the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:205196:22"/> or cheife Citie <hi>Stoel-VVeissenbourgh, Alba Regalis,</hi> where in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times the Kings of <hi>Hungary</hi> were usually Crowned and buried; it hath three Suburbs, and is well fortified, insomuch, that you can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enter in, nor come out, save onely over wooden Bridges, lyeth in a Valley, and not able to be approached unto, yea the very Suburbs are walled about to defend against an enterprise: but yet the heat of Summer cannot defend them from many reigning Countrey sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, so that it is very unwholsome to dwell there, hardly a League from thence, by the water <hi>Ballatonlake,</hi> you have the Fortress <hi>Siget,</hi> fensed round about with Morasses and Quagmires, devided into three partes, into which you must go over two Bridges: this Fortress was besieged by <hi>Solyman,</hi> and the Moates filled up with baggs of Wool, but was so courageously defended by the Count <hi>Seryn,</hi> that <hi>Solyman</hi> was forced to leave the Siege, with the loss of 26000 Turkes: you may also see in our Mapp <hi>Serynswar,</hi> situated near the River <hi>Dravus,</hi> Count <hi>Nicholas Seryn</hi> began to build this his Fortresse in <hi>Iune</hi> 1661 when as the Turkes had overmastered the Fortress <hi>Canisia</hi> in <hi>Styer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke;</hi> he made choice of a place not far from a Moras or Quagmir lying near a Water called the <hi>Michic,</hi> and did with assistance of many people, (which were well affected to him, who brought Carts and Materialls thither) build the same, insomuch that the Mill and Fortye-houses were built, and stood defended, calling this place according to his name, that it belonged to the <hi>Seryns:</hi> and assoone as he from else<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where had gotten therein sixe brave pieces of Cannon, The Turks were incensed, and threatned him, that if hee did not demolish the same they would come and visit him: this Order came not alone from the Grand <hi>Signior</hi> out of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> but there was also an Embas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadour sent to the German Emperour, who most earnestly desired the demollishing of the said place <hi>Serynswar;</hi> in the meane time the said Count proceeded with his fortification, and brought his Lady also therein: The <hi>Bashaw</hi> of <hi>Canisia</hi> perceiving that there was little to be done with him by force, put on the Foxes skin, and sent to the Count, and asked if this was don by order of the German Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>Seryn</hi> bad him to tell the <hi>Bashaw,</hi> that hee was not obliged to give him an account thereof (although it was the Emperours plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure) for it was upon his Ground and Territory that this Fortress was
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:205196:22"/> built for defence of his Kingdome, the <hi>Bashaw</hi> proceeded further hereupon (because that hee understood that every day more and more Ordinance and Ammunition came therein) and demanded, that seeing there was peace between the Turkish and German Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, why hee brought so much Cannon upon the Walls of his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tress; the Count well knowing that he had to deale with a Foxe, gave this answer, because hee but lately before had caused a great, Wood which lay very neare to his Fortress, to be cutt downe, that this was done to keepe of the Wolves, Bears, and other wild beasts from his Walls; The <hi>Bashaw</hi> well understanding his double meaning answer, sent no more Messengers after that time to the Count, but to the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kish Court, where hee propounded, that such a Fortress ought not to be tolerated in the face of <hi>Turkey,</hi> being a great disadvantage to the Turkes, being situated between a Morass and two Rivers, where ends the one and other Island, and the land was incompassed with little waters or Moores, having no Hills thereabout neare to hurt it, that the same was environed about with strong high Walls, and deepe Ditches or Moates: a shelter or defence to the lands on the other side the <hi>Donaw,</hi> and a protection to <hi>Comorra</hi> and <hi>Raab:</hi> you may there also see above the cheife Citie <hi>Vienna,</hi> the Hungarian Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis <hi>Presburgh</hi> situated on the <hi>Donaw</hi> tenn Leagues from <hi>Vienna,</hi> in a very faire convenient and healthfull pleasant place: the Hills lying thereabouts towards the Sun rising, are all planted with Vines and Trees, on the side of the River <hi>Donaw,</hi> it is full of Gardens, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure places, Meadows; and Corne-grounds, it hath also a Castle upon a Hill which is likewise called <hi>Presburgh:</hi> but whereas the Turkes by treachery (as is beleeved) upon the 27 of <hi>September</hi> 1663 got <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hausell,</hi> and that they came from thence before <hi>Presburgh</hi> (in which place the Count <hi>Montecuculli</hi> the Imperial Generall lay sicke) it was thought good to fortifie the same, which was before onely defended as against an enterprise with Turne-pikes, and encompassed with a strong Wall) which they as one man began in <hi>October</hi> following, making one whole and vast worke to defend all even to the <hi>Donaw:</hi> The <hi>Bashaw</hi> of <hi>Offen</hi> hearing this newes, required their allegiance, and promised the Inhabitants, that they for three yeares space should be free from all burthens and Taxes; but they within refused the prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:205196:23"/> and fortified both day and night the said Citie; for otherwise if this Citie had been lost, all the lands over the <hi>Donaw,</hi> also <hi>Raab, Comorra</hi> and <hi>Serynswar,</hi> would have been as cut of from <hi>Germany:</hi> but <hi>Serynswar</hi> may be attacqued on the side of <hi>Italy.</hi> The Count <hi>Seryn</hi> having taken Councell with the Imperiall Officers; he suddenly went over the <hi>Donaw</hi> to <hi>Comorra,</hi> to joyne himselfe to certain thousands of Hungarians, Polanders and others; whereupon the Turks refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying <hi>Newhausell,</hi> with their greatest Forces followed the Count; the effects whereof and what this Winter will produce about <hi>Ʋicegrad,</hi> or elsewhere be pleased to expect in a second part together with the description of <hi>Serynswar,</hi> with its fortifications; and likewise of <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> the Fortresses <hi>Comorra, Raab,</hi> and other places yet belonging to the Christians, which are at present in agitation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:205196:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>